Friends, in our last video we
learned about the Rig Veda. Of the four Vedas
From the oldest and most famous Vedas.
Oath proth is from Indra Ji's warrior energy
The Vedas laid the foundation of Indian culture.
Today we will discuss another Veda.
A Veda which, like the Rig Veda,
was not revealed in the sunlight but in the shadows of the night.
It was hidden in the Vedas. A Veda that
was not recognized as a real Veda for many centuries.
And a Veda that you will find
not on the battlefield of the Vedic period but in a mysterious
takes you deep into the jungle. Friends,
I welcome you to the mysterious
Atharvaveda.
Whenever the Vedas are discussed, people
The Atharva Veda is listed fourth in the list of the four Vedas . So, you might think so.
One might think that the Atharva Veda is the newest Veda.
But that's not the case. The truth is that there are thousands of
For years, there used to be only the Trai. Trai
means the three Vedas: Rigveda, Yajurveda,
The Samaveda and the Atharvaveda
were not considered part of this holy trinity. And when finally
The Atharva Veda's recognition
was met with considerable hesitation. But why?
This is because the knowledge in the Atharvaveda
is of a slightly different type.
It was dedicated to grand concepts.
For the growth of the kingdom, the kings and emperors
For blessings, for Soma Yagna,
Atharva Veda is not for such grand things
It was about people like you and me,
common people and their common problems.
To avoid illness, to cure snake venom, to
defeat enemies, to make someone your own
Falling in love, protecting children,
peace in the home. All of the things that a Vedic
People who care about themselves
may be due to their practical nature .
The Atharva Veda did not receive as much respect as the other three Vedas .
The Atharva Veda contains not only such spells
but also some deep philosophies. Some of the
Most Profound Upanishads Like The Mundaka
Upanishad, Mandukya Upanishad, Prashna Upanishad
All of this is connected to the Atharva Veda. And most
interestingly, through the Atharva Veda, we
There is much to learn about our ancient history
. Who was this sage Atharva?
What connection did he have with Iran? And
why do we hear echoes of Indra in the Atharva Veda?
Instead, we find a more subtle presence of Varuna.
Let's explore this mysterious passage from the Atharva Veda.
On a jungle safari. Do you know what
Atharva Veda is all about? Let's begin.
Vriksham Labuja
Samantam
Parashaswaje
In the world of fear
[music]
Yatha Makaso
[Music]
Yatha Man Paka As
Like
the fall of Garuda, the wings are not earthly
Evahate
The mind
is like a lustful one
[Music]
Yatha Man Paka Asaha
The lines you just heard That was a love
chat used to make someone fall in love with you
The mantra comes from the sixth chapter of the Atharvaveda, one
of the 20 chapters into which the Atharvaveda is divided.
Two versions of the Atharvaveda survive today. One is Shaunaka
version and a Papla version. At one time,
there were nine such versions in total. Each one of
them corresponding to a particular branch.
Shanak is the standard one which continuously
It's been going on. And
that's what we'll use as a reference in this video today. The Other Version
It is called Pipla Adar version which
was found in Kashmir for the first time in 1873.
Unfortunately, it was in a corrupt state
. Then, surprisingly, in 1953
Entomologist Durga Mohan Bhattacharya
found Pipla in a village in Odisha.
A fully intact
manuscript of the tradition. It includes the Shaunaka version
There are more mantras. And scholars have been
comparing the two versions to provide new insights.
Discovering. The first thing you'll
notice about the Other Veda is that it's nothing
Things are very strange. Some mantras
are three lines long, while others are two lines long.
Some are just one line prose
. Some have a longer first line, so
The next one is short. The ending is also dry,
with each mantra consisting of just two words.
Based on the language used of the
Atharvaveda, scholars believe that some parts of
The Atharvaveda could actually be even older than
the Rigveda. The 20 cantos of the Atharvaveda are divided into four
It is divided into layers. Books
1 to 7 are called the early layers.
This is the Age of Magic, when some
mysterious spells were popular. Since the 8th century
The 12th chapter
is called the middle layer. This is the edge of the mind. When the Atharvaveda
Philosophy was most developed in
the 13th to 18th centuries .
is said. This is the age where most of
the Hindu rituals from funeral to
Marriage they got formulated. And the last two
books, 19 and 20, are the appendix layers.
in which verses from the Rig Veda were kind of
adopted into the Atharva Veda. It's like a
covered to make the Atharva Veda more acceptable to
the thought leaders of that time.
use the terms early, middle, and late,
it may seem like this is purely a
Chronological ordering. But this
is not exactly correct. I have analyzed the 20 cantos of the Atharvaveda.
The hymns of the Vedas are arranged vertically,
with the number of mantras in each hymn being
The darker and taller it becomes. We see
that almost all the books in the early
The layers are arranged in an ascending order of
mantra count. Here the mantras are
Relatively short and quite simple.
If you look at the middle and late layers, then notice
How they are significantly darker. Meaning,
there are a lot of mantras, but every
Soap. It is very different from the initial
layer. And finally comes the appendix.
It was stuffed with a lot of insulation
. Now we'll go layer by layer and
Let's see exactly what
's going on in each layer. Part One: The Early Layers. When people
Let 's talk about the spooky nature of the Atharvaveda.
It is mostly this layer that
They are talking about this. This is the layer of
magic that separates the Atharva Veda from the rest of the Vedas.
Compare makes it quite unique. Like
a pharmacist to cure diseases
mantras, Ayushyani mantras for long life
and nourishing mantras for happiness and prosperity.
Of course the infamous Aachar Mantra i.e. extreme
black magic through which you can control someone very much.
You can also cause harm. Fortunately,
there are also protective spells that you can use on others.
You can avoid people's magical spells.
And beyond these, we also find spells for
Daily regular use. For example, how can you win at gambling ? You're safe while traveling.
How can you survive? How can you protect yourself with amulets ? All such
There are also many prayers for fulfilling wishes
. People believe that
The mantras of the Atharva Veda
have some inherent magical quality.
What they mean is different but simply these
sounds and vibrations have a magical power.
It's kind of like an ancient form
of manifestation that you can use through mantras.
You can literally bend reality by
... I guess you might be feeling how this is
Kind of connected to Tantra and your
intuition would be right.
Going beyond the layer we
find many gems like Ayurveda Tantra and Shaivika Agamas.
There for the Atharva Veda is a mirror
of the concerns of everyday society of the Vedic period.
Of priorities. A society where there
were no doctors or police. So this is that.
The time of the society when language
was developing to describe order and care.
The Atharvaveda has historically been referred to by many names . From Amritveda to
Atma Veda, Angira Veda, Brahma Veda, Atharva
Veda, Angi Rasa Veda, Bhargava Rasa Veda, Kshatriya
Veda, Chandoveda. There's a story behind each name
. But let's just focus on two of them.
Dees, Atharvasa and Bhargava Angarsa. All these
words refer to three Rishi families.
Atharvas who come from sage Atharva. Angirasas
who come from the sage Angira and Bhargavaz
Come from the sage Bhrigo. These three sage families
seemed to be there even before the Rigveda was
composed. Because in the Rigveda itself they
are referred to as ancestors.
The interesting thing is that all three
of these names have a connection to fire.
The word is linked to fire or embers
. The word Atharvan may have come from Atar.
Which is an Iranian word for fire. And
brigu comes from the root word brik meaning
A spark. So, realistically, it seems that
these names are used to refer to fire.
Priests who may have lived before the creation of the Vedas
. Ten evidences to show that these three
Atharva would be the oldest of the names.
The oldest mandalas of the Rigveda, i.e., the sixth
The Mandala states that the sages
used to churn fire like the Atharvas in ancient times.
Even the Mundaka Upanishad, which is linked
to the Atharva Veda, begins with a
With the story. Brahma Ji, the creator of all
and the sustainer of the world, emerges
He is the first God. He gives Brahma Vidya which
is the basis of all sciences to his son
They pass to the Atharvan. Brahma is
the firstborn of the gods
The creator of the universe, the building, the cow,
all Brahma, knowledge, all knowledge, reputation
Atharva to his eldest son Pra
then Atharva gave this knowledge to the sage Angiras
So essentially
according to the Mundaka Upanishad, the Atharvas came first and
Then the Angiras might have followed later.
The Atharvas are also described in the Chulaka Upanishad.
It is said to be the ancestors of the Pragus. By
the way, it is also in the Zoroastrian religion of Iran.
Their priests
were called Atharvas or Atharvas. Meaning at a time when India and
The people of Iran used to be one, so their common
priests might have been called Atharvas.
The texts also indicate that the
first layer is Bheshagam, meaning happiness and peace.
The mantras of
were developed by the clan of sage Bhrigu. While those of black magic
Components were developed by the
clan of sage Angiras. Since the name is Bhargava
Angarsa is described in the Atharvaveda as an
alloy which is a black magic metal and a white
Made of magic metal.
Like a peacock
[music]
from zero
of
[music]
In
Desa
[music]
Let us now move
to the second layer of the Atharvaveda, from Books 8 to Books 12, which is called the Age of
Mind will say here the sages of Atharvaveda are less into magic
spells and mysteries of the universe
For example, in the 10th chapter
we get Skambhasu the Him of
The Cosmic Pillar. The sage is asking
what is this invisible pillar that holds this entire universe together.
What holds up the universe? What does the Earth
rest on and what supports the sky?
Is it? Kasminange
tash land rasya kasminange
Tash
Kasminange
tash
the best
Give
Doesn't All That Kind of Remind You of the Nas
Suta Kima
Kas Shame
Kima Gahanam Gabhim
which also asks what was the world's
Who knows the Ad Veda before the creation
where the Rig Veda was fascinated by what of the world
Tha Otherway Seems to Be More Interested in the
How of Things Then in the Ninth Chapter We
It is found in Kamasukta, The Hem of Desire. Here it
is said that desire came first.
Rahe Ho Na Kamna first came before For the
Gods, before the Ancestors and before even
Human desire created the universe
. That might almost seem blasphemous.
To people today. Where not having desires
is the most vicious value. And then the 12th
In the Sukta we find the Bhumis. And
historian Meenakshi Jain even says that
The Bhumi Sukta could very well be the first
anthem of humanity. Atharva Veda. Atharva Veda
There is a Sukhata in me. It is called Prithvi
Sukhata. And historians say that my
It doesn't have to be said. It is called the First National
Song of the World.
Asmato
[Music]
Humans
whose or mountains are equal
Nana Viriya Aushadhiya
Vivarti
In the Prithvi Na Prathata Ram Na Prithvi Sukta,
the Earth repeatedly says, "Cut me."
No, don't share me. I'm like a cow
. I'll milk you whenever you want to wash me.
I will give it. She repeatedly says that
all the people who live above me are theirs.
Their speech is different. Their clothing is different. Their
food is different. But I treat them all equally.
This is where we get the phrase "mother land "
Putro aham prithvi matlab earth is my mother
and I am her son ok remember this
We heard a song at the start of the segment.
There, too, the question was, "
How is this world made? How does it stand? Guess what?"
That was actually a mantra from the
Holy Book of the Zoroastrians. Yes,
Avesta. Well, technically the Persian translation
of Avesta, which is actually Vedic Sanskrit.
but both these texts are thousands of years and thousands of kilometers apart.
were taken away. So
why do so many of these questions have a common thread? Was this just a
Coincidence?
Coincidence? I think not.
In the previous video we learned how Rigveda
is primarily a document of the Angarsa clan.
Top 10 Rishi Clans include Kanva Rishi, Gautama
Rishi, Bhardwaj Rishi, Gritsamada Rishi and
Vamadeva. These are all Angaras sub clans
which makes the contribution of the overall
The Angaras clan is about 50% of the Rig Veda,
so they are very much the main characters.
The Angaras worshipped the gods, whose
chief was Indra. And as you know, Indra would
Represents desire
. Represents action
They do. Indra doesn't follow anyone's rules
. He makes his own. If
Indra ji is called Gandhi ji, O Indra
there is enough for everyone, need not for
Everyone's greed. So Indra says to him,
"Oh, how cute? Go tell this to the demons."
Say it. Gandhiji, it is because of my greed that
your needs are being fulfilled.
Desire is good. Power is good. This is kind
of like what Niebuhr and Plato discuss about.
Justice in the Greek culture.
According to Plato, justice is doing good and
Being part of the natural order. When every human being
understands their responsibility in society,
If he performs his
duties properly, he establishes justice in society overall.
He
thinks that this is just a social
Constructs. What weak people create to control stronger people . Which is true
I am powerful, I do whatever I want without anyone's permission.
Ask for it. Look, the Vedas are completely self-
aware that Indra has many flaws.
They know Indra is jealous,
violent, and lustful. He's always
He is engrossed in it. And yet, Angaras
can never tire of singing Indra's praises. Why? Because
Despite all his faults, Indra gets the job
done. He helps you win wars. He helps
You become powerful. Atharva Veda 7.5.8 says
that in my right hand are my winnings.
And in my left hand is my victory. Indra,
give me cows, horses, wealth, and gold. So,
Indira is kind of like a lucky charmer
who helps with gambling. Look, Angras people.
If he were at Hogwards, he
would probably be part of the Gryffindor house.
The adventurous ones. They
weren't afraid to break the rules. And they are kind of
Like the Greeks in some ways with whom they
share this Indo-European madness.
In fact, there are many
religious parallels between Greece and India.
Was this whole thing of the younger gods
replacing the older gods? The Olympians
Replacing the Titans. In the Indian
context, we also had Dawatas.
Replacing the Asuras. The new replacing
the old. The other Greek gods have a lot of
Logos, Zeus, Aries, Apollo. We see these
men as powerful, passionate, and lustful.
Some cheat, some drink alcohol
. These people celebrate the joys of life.
And it seems like they're not
just tolerated for their floss, but more so
They are loved because of their flaws. Possibly
because it made them relatable. Also India
Both Greek and Roman cultures
are very visual cultures.
Concrete forms are given
in the form of icons. Regarding Greek statues,
You know. And Indian architecture.
And the more I read about it,
It seems to me that they
don't see the world in black and white.
The world is a spectrum. And every
creature is like a mongoose. It has a type.
There's a weight, there's a height. Everything
has a personality, a
Personification happens. So,
they seem to be more open to this kind of diversity.
The Angres family's patron deity was
Brihaspati. Represented by Jupiter.
He was the chief priest of the gods who provided strategic counsel to Indra in their
Wars Against the Asuras. And who
can tell me who the Patron of the Asuras is?
Shukracharya, that's right. And
who was Shukracharya's father? Oh my God. Sage Pragu.
The pattern is clear. The sage Angas
was a leader of the Vedic civilization.
Closer to the Indo-European culture, there
was another lineage that shaped Vedic culture.
The griffins of Angirasce represent this culture in contrast to Dorian
adventurism .
The Raven Clones were stable in 1990. They
worshipped the Old Gods in a formless state.
He preferred order to will,
purity to power, and polytheism to
Instead of monotheism, this tradition was followed
by the Bhrigus, the top two authors of the Atharva Veda.
The sages are Atharvas and Bhrigus. Notice
that the Rigveda ranks lowest in the list.
While the Rigveda is dominated by the Angirasa Rishis , the Atharvaveda
Bhrigu dominates energy. Vaise is
much more cultural in Angiras and Bhrigu
Differences are what we shall talk about, but the
fundamental difference is what defines all the rest.
Differences arise. Seem to be
about their thoughts about the afterlife.
What happens after death? In Vedic times,
after the afterlife, the soul took two highways.
One was Devayana, meaning the paths
of the gods, and the other was Pitriyana, meaning the path of the
Ancestors. Devayana went directly to
Brahmaloka, after which one attained salvation.
This was the recommended path that the British
strove to achieve.
The path is also called Uttarayan.
In Pitayana the soul goes only to the moon world, from where
It makes a U-turn and respawns back
on Earth. One path is for the gods, and the other is for the
of the ancestors. And it seems like the Angarases
and Bhrigus had their own favourites. Bhrigu who
They were paternal followers and practiced ancestor worship
. In the Mahabharata, the Devas were considered the younger sons of the Asuras.
Bhai has been said, which symbolically
implies that Asuras were the Older Gods.
Sage Bhrigu used to offer sacrifices to both gods and demons . But for him
The most prominent demon was Varuna Deva. You can imagine
that he was equally loved by the Bhargavas.
Angiras had as many Indras, or perhaps even
more. For example, the fourth Mandala of the Rigveda
I say, "I am King Varuna. I
have been given demonic powers."
Even the gods will agree. I am the king of all humans
. According to the Atreya Brahman
Bhrigu himself got the title of Varuni,
that is, the son of Varuna. Where Indra Ji Will
While Lord Varuna is
the god of cosmic order, i.e., night.
From an outside perspective, nighttime sleep is self-regulated. It
operates at its own pace. It is governed by one's desires.
Not from. So you cannot change the results of your actions by coaxing any God .
Order and harmony are automatically maintained through the seasons .
To do so means to follow Dharma. This is what
protects life. So Varuna is the Plato.
Varuna is now
considered a boring ocean god after the Puranic reshuffle .
Like the Greek Positon, but
in the Rig Veda, Varuna seems to be the ultimate sky.
The god worshipped by the Aryans after Dasa and before Indra . In the Rigveda
Varun ji has received a lot of praise. For
example, a mantra says, Varun ji
I can see the trajectory of birds flying in the sky .
The ship's path is also known
. It also shows which way the wind will blow.
Varun knows what
is and what will happen. In fact, our former
President APJ Abdul Kalam
while launching his book Wings of Fire
A mantra from the Atharva Veda was used
.
Uto samudro varunas gukshi utasmin alp
udake neelin, that is, this earth belongs to Varuna.
This limitless sky is His. This water
is also contained within Him. And yet He is in this water.
hidden in even a drop of water.
I love this just previous mantra. It says
Whether you're standing still, walking, or
hiding somewhere. Whenever two people think they're
When they are talking privately, Varun
is present between them as a third witness who
The One who sees everything knows everything
. Indra doesn't seem to care much.
About sin, virtue, and all that. But
this is not the case with Varuna. In the Rigveda
While writing some of the funeral suktas
the sage seemed to be scared of Varuna.
For example, it is said in Rigveda 7864, O
Varun Dev, what mistake have I committed that
You took away my friend who
used to sing your praises, tell me Lord, take away my sins.
Take and then there is Rigveda 786 six
in this mantra we know Varuna hum pe kin
We impose restrictions on things, it means we
will not harm ourselves as much as
Seduction, thoughtlessness, alcohol, gambling and anger
will do, so you see the contrast, Indra on one side
is being worshipped for helping in gambling
and on the other hand it is being said that Varun
Dev, we will not indulge in alcohol, gambling, or anger
. Varun ji was also the
The ultimate judge. Atharva Veda 1.10.2 says,
I offer my obeisances to King Varuna,
His anger, his fierceness that
tests every lie. O Varuna, I am yours
And I have been bringing thousands of people.
Bless your servant to live for 100 years.
Notice how the Vedic mantras start taking
a devotional-like property. Varuna is seen as a
Omniscient, omnipresent, a silent watcher.
Where Indra acts, Varuna
Observe. Where Indra concurs
, Varuna judges. Where Indra
Varuna is the god of warriors, while Varuna
is the god of priests and kings.
It is often associated with imagery of a flame burning underwater .
At some places he is also called the Apam
Napath which means the nephew. and nephew of the
Water's either of them. So this fire inside the
water, it gives a strange kind of wipe.
It's like an internally subdued kind of
fire. This could also be because Bhrigu seems to
Be coast loving people. There
is a town in Gujarat called Bharuch. In ancient times it was called Bhriguk
It was also called Kutch, which literally means
Bhrigu's marshland. This town is situated on the banks of the Narmada.
Located at the opening of the river, it
would have been a very easy place to trade.
In the Puranas, Goddess Lakshmi
is said to be the daughter of sage Bhrigu. Evidenced by Her
Alternative names are Bhargavi and Bhrigu's Daughter.
This suggests a possible connection to the Bhrigus.
It could also be due to wealth and trade. Think
of the merchant navy of that time. So, this location
used to expose the Bhrigus to other
cultures including Asaria, Acadia,
In Babylon, Iran, Arabia, these cultures
followed Semitic culture, not Indo-European.
which is also a language
family to which Hebrew, Aramaic, Arabic
This all belongs to. By the way, I also
find it fascinating that the capital of Assyria
The Asura. Where people worshipped the Asura.
Who was one of the many gods of the beginning
The impact of this cultural exchange
can still be seen in India today.
You get it through practices like illusion.
You know that sound which women make, called
Also called hulhuli or uruli, it's
a distinctly Sumerian practice.
This tradition is still alive today, from the East to the coastal regions of India .
Families eventually
made the Gangetic heartland their stronghold. They settled in regions like
Hastinapur and Kurukshetra and even
expanded in words. Brugus but border
They lived in areas like Gujarat.
According to the Puranas, Bhrigu had two sons. One was
Venus,
named after Friday, was also the Guru of the
Asuras and he was the master of the Sanjivani
Vidya. The other was Chavanji. Yes, the same.
The cow who invented Chavanprash. He was the great grandfather
of sages Jamadagni and Parashurama.
So Bhagus Were a Pretty Big Deal and Notice
How Bhagus Stungly Associated with Healing
This is being done with all these herb
preferences. This will later become the basis of Ayurveda and
Unani medicine
is transformed into systems. Look if you look at the culturists
Observe, you will see that humans
create their own gods in their own lives.
When humans conceive a form for gods
, they often project their own ideals
On to their gods. The trades they
value in themselves are the trades they value in themselves.
They also search among the gods. The beetles
had a great fondness for wisdom. Varuna
is described in many instances as the God who possesses Vice or Wisdom.
For example, Rigveda 7.87.4 refers to Varuna as a scholar. Other contexts
In it is the link to the word Vedas which
also means wisdom. Now guys, it's time
For the big reveal. The moment that this entire
video was building up toward. Author
Jitendra Chatterjee writes in his book Atharva Zathustra that this word is found in the Vedas eventually.
would have led to a term like medhas also
meaning intelligence. So asura methas which
Eventually Becomes Ahura Masta
Zoroastrianism's Most Supreme Formless
God. So Aurasta is none other than our own
Varuna Deva. Okay, if that seems too
Indirect and convoluted consider that
Zoroastrian text Kharada state in the
List that describes 101 names of Ahura Mazda . Check out What's Your 44 Name
Oh my God that means the Supreme God of Iran
is none other than Varun Dev of India.
In the last video, we saw
how Hinduism has many gods.
It seems like a similar
assimilation happened here. Varuna of the Aryans
God Who Was Mofad on the Indo-European
Uranus Assimilates into the Semitic God
Asura Creating the First of Its Kind
Monotheistic God Ahura Masta The Base of
What Would Later Become the God of the Entire
Abrahamic World, But We Are Getting to Ahead
Of Ourselves. Part Three Late Stage. The
Late Stage of the Other Veda is Talking About a
The time when the divorce of Indo-Iranian cultures
was finalized. Now there was a common culture.
had gone in separate directions.
After deliberating at the Edge of Mind ,
This is a society based on ideals and
on the basis of those ideals it tries to mould its societies.
For example, between books 13 and 18,
there are three books which said the foundation.
of the Hindu culture. Book 14 is completely
dedicated to marriage-related rituals. Today
The backbone of all those mantras comes
From this part of the Atharva Veda. Book 18
discusses another aspect of life, namely, Antyeshti.
Funeral rituals are described. So these
two books solidify two very important
Aspects of any human's life. But very
interestingly, Book 15 is called The Vratya
Kand. This entire Kand is dedicated to
this vrat character. Represents a person
Who is having matted hair who goes into a
trans while dancing. And that society's
Almost stays outside. Seeming like a non-
Vedic yogi. Well, guys, this is the beginning.
Of the process of absorption of Rudra.
This is the description of a proto Shiva
character. From here we see that
the process of Aryan religion had begun.
A complete transformation into Hinduism, or Sanatana Dharma . Parallel Around
12 BC A Hotri, or
a Joutar, appears in Iranian religion. Called Patriarch
Zarathustra. His name probably meant a
golden camel. In English it is called
Zoroaster. At the age of 30, Zoroaster
receives a divine vision.
Ahura Mazdar himself contacts them directly
and appoints his messenger.
He continued to propagate this new religion under the patronage of King Vishtaspa until his death.
They set about establishing it. Their
central message is humata, hukta,
Huwashta means good thoughts, good words, and
good deeds. Follow these three things and
Ahora Mastada will give you salvation.
But the true radical reform of Zarathustra
Monotheism is the way of preaching.
In Iran and Arabia before Zoroaster
Many gods were worshipped, for
example, the Semitic sky god Elom-Hobal.
Ishtar. Zoroaster divided these multiple gods
with different qualities into just two.
Distilled into archetypes:
Ahramasta the Good and Angrahamanu the Evil.
In Yasna 32 Zarathustra says, "All you gods
give birth to evil thoughts. Lies and
You have been corrupted by your ego. The people who
do the most evil things are the ones
They become your favorites. Do you understand? So Zarathustra: Here is directly
Addressing how Indra, Agni, Vayu are all
problematic because they incentivize
Bad behavior. No wonder he was super pist
of our Vedic Rishis the Angarasas. Possibly
Which is why Angramanyu might be
connected with Angarsa. He professed monotheism
caste, system,
exclusive, a priest, class
Removed all concepts and
made the religion more accessible. Animal Sacrifice
It was completely banned.
The concept of yajna was fading away in India.
In favor of this new cool thing called
meditation. But Zoroaster in Parsheia
They made fire worship a central
part of their religion. You don't know this about the Baha'is.
Do you know? Yes, the same Lotus Temple
religion. I didn't believe in their religion.
It is said that God has progressively revealed
himself to humanity. First Age
Abraham then Krishna then Moses then
Zoroaster then Buddha Christ and Prophet
Muhammad and his two priests followed him
. So, from their perspective, Zoroaster
Reformed Indo-Iranian culture in the same way as Krishna did.
Directly from Zoroastrianism
It was influenced by Judaism,
the religion of Jesus. Concepts like one supreme God,
Good versus evil, heaven versus hell,
all this Zoroastrianism gave to Judaism
From Judaism, these ideas then
passed into Christianity. And finally
Islam
probably adopted monotheism or tawhid as its core principle from Christianity.
fundamental. I have come to believe
that Islam is a very very very very very
Strictly monotheistic face.
Many of Islam's concepts are based in
Jordanism and very interestingly both
religions have a bridge described which
connects the human realm
with heaven. Both religions believe that
For believers, this bridge widens
and becomes easier to cross.
And for those who have had scenes with non-believers,
it's a razor's edge.
As thin as it gets. Making it
impossible for you to cross and fall off inu
The Zoroastrians know this bridge
as Chinvat Peretu. While in Islam
This is the Bridge of Sirat Reference in One of
the Mostant Surat in Islam. Suratul Fatiha
Iya nabad wa Iya nastaeen
Ina Sirat Mustaqeem
Sirat Lazna An Al Gair Mag Alai One
In India, the story took a slightly different direction.
Varun's spirit doesn't exist here.
It was transmuted into classical Indian fashion .
Medha Tithi Rishi of the clan has
mentioned in the Atharvaveda that Vishnu and Varuna are worshipped together.
Write the mantra. Atharva Veda 7.25.1,
for example, says this in the morning
I pray to Vishnu and Varuna
, gods whose power no one can match.
You two are the most powerful and
foremost among the mighty. Even Indra and Vishnu
Added together by sage Praskhandvara in Atharvaveda
7.44.1
Wrote. I mean composed. Indra and Vishnu,
you both conquered. Never defeated.
O Indra and Vishnu, when you
fought your battle, this entire infinite world with its
Three zones were created. Slowly and
gradually, Varun ji's qualities
Largely, Vishnu shifted to Vishnu.
Visually, for example, Vishnu in the Vedas.
was described as a short Vamana form,
but later Varuna's majestic form
The imagery, that cosmic vastness, that all-seeing
nature, the blue skin, the ocean symbolism, it all adds up
Bhrigu, who had been a devotee of Varuna, became Vishnu's devotees.
He began to transform into a devotee. This
story is famously captured in the mythology.
Story where Rishi Bhrigu tries to test who
among the three Tridevs will be the first in the yajna
Who should be worshipped? Bhrigu went
to Brahma, but he was engrossed in meditation.
They are. So, out of ego, they reject him
. Then he goes to Shiva.
But he's probably angry and busy
. So he rejects him as well. Then when
He goes to Lord Vishnu, who
is resting on Sheshnag.
When he did not get up, he became angry and
kicked Vishnu in the chest.
He does not get angry. Instead , pressing the feet of sage Bhrigu, he says, O sage, your
Are your legs hurting? Bhrigu ji
melts away and accepts him. This is
Because he saw Varuna's qualities in Vishnu , such as kindness, humility, and good will.
Words, wisdom. Where Vishnu took over the
icon from Varuna. Shiva is increasing
Worshipped in an iconic form. The
God who represents the Nirguna, the
Formless. No wonder Advaita philosophy naturally
aligns with Shaivism. Shaivism also
Absorbed a lot of the antiquated
properties of this time. Which gave birth
To later movements like the Nath sect or
Lingayatism, where caste is actively
Challenged. In fact, the Bhargava's
later sages, such as Parashurama and Shiva,
He was a great devotee of Varuna. So it seems like the
same archetype of the wrath holder Varuna
He received very different
treatment in India and Iran.
Masculine aspects
were extracted to form Ahmasta. While the feminine
Aspects were distilled to Anahita the
Goddess of Water, who is probably Semitic
There may have been influence from Ishtar. There was
a goddess called Mithra who lived in some areas of Iran.
He was super popular in
India and he was regarded as the God of Contracts.
Varun's feminine aspects
were preserved. And even he was
Paired with Mitra. 88% of the
times Mitra and Varuna are listed in the Rigveda
Together. And the Puranas and their
postmodernist twist that Varun and Mitra have
Sort of like lovers. They are
compared to two half moons. Which is the waxing moon
It means the waxing moon
is represented by Neptune and
The waning moon
is represented by Mitra. Bhagavata Purana
In this, Varun and Mitra are said to have given
birth to Rishi Vashisht and Rishi Agastya through
An Asexual Process. Varuna as
Ara Mazda in Europe Shaped How Folk Saw God the Father
But Mitra became a full-blown cult called
Mitra. A Roman religion before Christianity
The major military region was Mitrism. This was
kind of like a secret brotherhood.
There used to be underground meeting places
that looked like caves and they called them
Mitriums. And these
were springing up all over the place where soldiers would meet and socialize.
In fact, it is believed
that Mitra's birthday was on December 25th.
A thing that turns out to be Jesus Christ
's birthday, according to a Bible story.
The night baby Jesus was born, he
was visited by three messengers bearing gifts.
They are called Magi. Magi was the term
used in Western Iran for Zor Astridians.
Priests. This term comes from the Old
Iranian word magupati which means something
Like the God of Maya. This is
also where we get terms like magic and magician.
Interestingly, a community
of Brahmins also exists in India called Maga.
The Brahmans trace their lineage to these Iranian priests.
The last two books of the Atharvaveda
are almost copy-pasted from the Rigveda.
All the Asuraic Bhrigu related text. You
can imagine Angaras Pandit a little bit atharvaveda
Hence the heavy dose of Indira devotion injected into the last two episodes.
But, as you can probably agree,
the Atharva Veda has a different vibe. It is about those Bhrigu
Kaa Energy is the OG Skeptical Stoic
Purity Focused Ancestor Washing
Mercantiles were formless God loving people.
Who gave the whole world the blessings of Varun Dev
Varun Dev or
Ahmasta is the best template for all the
Gods in most of Asia and Europe. Whether
you call him Vishnu or Krishna or
Christ or Allah or Shiva. You
call it the same all-judging, all-knowing Father of humanity.
You're worshipping. Westerners
call India a morganically pagan nation. This comes.
From the Latin word paganos literally meaning
villagers or rustics. Islam in its pre
He calls the Islamic path Jahiliyah, meaning
the Age of Ignorance. Back in the dark days.
In Arabia and Europe, when someone
conquered you, he would attack your temple.
I would come and place idols of my gods.
And worst of all, there were many in society
There were also evil practices, like child sacrifice.
According to Islamic texts, in Mecca
In fact , a moon god named Hubal was worshipped just near the Kaaba .
A bull-shaped metal statue that was hollow inside
. Its hands were as if it were
Seeking a sacrifice. This idol
had many grooves. Where your
There was a sacrifice offer. If you
brought only flour or sugar, you would get the first batch.
Bird to 2, Sheep to 3,Goat to 4
Calves to slot 5. Cows or horses
will go into slot 6 and slot
Seven were available if you
want to sacrifice your first newborn child
Yes. This ritual was also called Moloch. So
you can see how idols would have become a
A symbol of trauma for this culture.
When Zoroaster spoke out against such evil practices
He probably didn't know that the small
decision would have the snowball effect.
Centuries Later Wood Lead to the Destruction of
This Very Demonic Statue Along With
Thousands and Thousands of Other Such
Statues Across All of Arabia Under the
Direction of Prophet Muhammad. This is why
Islam has become so strong.
Prohibition of giving the Creator any
form. It is seen as an attempt to contain
The Infinite. Sadly, the cultists that
Zarathustra helped shape
For the same cultists
disproved Zoroastrianism and expelled it from Iran.
In India, the Angarasa spirit evolved to
accept every story. You call him Ram,
Whether I say Krishna, someone says Durga, someone
says Shiva, we all know him in our own way.
They are trying to touch a single element.
Advaita Vedanta has gone a step further.
Not only does it say that there is
one God and that that one God is the Creator.
But it adds that that One God is the Creation
Itself. You, me, this video, this conversation,
It's all the same consciousness. God is not watching
the universe. God is literally the universe.
Watching Itself. The monotheism of the West
is the monotheism of a desert. Where scarcity
Where order is essential for survival
. Where not being good enough means not
Surviving. Obviously there is no time
for singing and dancing. India's
Monotheism on the other hand
is the monotheism of a fertile land where variety of nature
This is the default setting. In one area, you'll
find both basil and weed.
There will be butterflies and there will be ants.
All contradictions co-exist.
When I started making this video
, I had no idea what
The Atharva Veda will teach me so much. I
now realize that it doesn't matter how far apart we are.
On some level, we're all deeply connected. If
you're still listening, I know for a long time.
It was a video. So thanks for focusing on it for so
long. If you liked the video, please like and comment.
Make sure you leave a comment and subscribe to
us. And if you really enjoyed it,
Then do consider sharing with friends on
WhatsApp or are a tie or whichever
Platform you're on. I'll be back with a
new video next time. Bye Good night!
India in Pixels Gets Your Mind TickingSubscribe for More Join the Mission.
Bright Keep Dream
India in Pixels, Thanks for tuning in